Literacy Volunteers of America (LVA) Records
Literacy Volunteers of America (LVA) Records
1965-1990
Literacy Volunteers of America.
30 linear ft.
Papers of the non-profit education and literacy organization founded in 1962 by Ruth J. Colvin in Syracuse, New York. Material in the collection includes audio tapes and cassettes, correspondence, motion pictures, newsletters, primers, readers, reports, slides and video tapes. Areas of special interest are English as a second language, work within correctional facilities, the production of readers and workbooks, involvement in the National Right to Read Effort, and the development of slide/tape and later video tutor training programs.
149430
Biographical History
Literacy Volunteers, Inc. was founded in 1962 by Ruth J. Colvin in Syracuse, New York. Mrs. Colvin's interest in literacy grew out of the global mission of her denomination and exposure to the work of Frank Laubach and Welthy Honsinger Fisher. Planning to encourage her church to support literature programs in Africa, Mrs. Colvin learned of the high number of illiterates in the United States. Focusing on the illiterate in her local area she gave over 90 presentations educating the community to the problem at hand. Thus LVA had its beginnings.
In 1972 the name was changed to Literacy Volunteers of America, Inc. or LVA. LVA is a nonprofit educational organization whose main aim is "to provide training and program support for volunteers who tutor adults and teenagers, one to one, to write and speak conversational English." A National Endowment for the Humanities grant in 1979 enabled the production of a bibliography of humanistic materials at low reading levels. In 1991 the organization had grown to over 400 programs in 33 states. Mrs. Colvin has traveled to over 40 countries presenting workshops and serving-as a consultant to literacy programs. Areas of special interest are: English as a Second Language: work within correctional facilities; literacy and public libraries; the production of readers and workbooks (READ ON!); involvement in the National Right to Read Effort and the development of slide/tape and later video tutor training workshops.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Literacy Volunteers of America Records covers the period 1965-1988 with the bulk falling between 1971 and 1985. The collection contains general office files as well as the papers of Ruth J. Colvin, founder of the organization. There is also a considerable amount of audiovisual material.
Four sequences of General Files, each arranged alphabetically, contain office records of the organization. Included here are administrative information (Board of Directors, task forces, committees, staff development), LVA publications and teaching material (workshops, flash cards, flip charts, "Read On!", etc.), conference programs and presentations, correspondence with individuals and organizations (ALA, NAPCAE, NEH, PEACE), and bibliographies and articles on relevant topics such as basic reading, literacy, and ESL.
Two sequences of Ruth Colvin material, each arranged alphabetically, contain Ms. Colvin's own correspondence and subject files relating to her work with the organization. Included here are conferences, travel to Australia and New Zealand, photographs, and tutor training material.
The collection also contains an extensive amount of Media, including audiotapes, audiocassettes, films, slides, and videos. Much of this consists of training material developed and used by LVA, but there are also recordings of awards ceremonies, interviews, speeches, workshops, seminars, and other events.
Arrangement of the Collection
Each of the four General Files series and the two Ruth Colvin series are arranged in their own separate A-Z order. The researcher is advised to explore the entire inventory to ensure locating all relevant material. Much of the material remains in original order and in original folders. Media is subdivided by type, and then arranged alphabetically by title within each type.
PLEASE NOTE: Labels on many of the audio and video cassettes, reels, tapes, and slides were missing or illegible. Information on cases or labels has been transcribed verbatim where possible, and may or may not be useful or accurate.
Related Material
has the papers of many individuals and organizations involved in adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing. In particular, see the
Laubach Literacy Records
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Colvin, Ruth J.; Root, Jane H.; Literacy Volunteers of America -- Archives.; National Endowment for the Humanities.; National Right to Read Effort.; Adult education -- United States.; English language -- Study and teaching -- Foreign speakers.; English language -- Textbooks for foreign speakers.; Libraries and new literates.; Literacy -- Australia.; Literacy -- United States.; Primers.; Libraries and illiterate persons.; Readers (Primary); Readers (Adult); Right to Read Program.; Tutors and tutoring.; 16mm (photographic film size); Audiocassettes.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Motion pictures (visual works); Newsletters.; Photographs.; Reports.; Slides (photographs); U-matic.; Videocassettes.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Literacy Volunteers of America.
Inventory
- General files (I)
  - Adult Basic Education - New York State (Box 1)
  - Adult Literacy Issues, Programs and Opinions (Box 1)
  - American Library Association [ALA], Apr. 4, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Articles, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - BBC Adult Literacy Handbook, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Basic Math, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Basic Reading
    - Action, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Assessment/Goal Setting, segment 5 (Box 1)
    - B4, first and third drafts; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Goals and Lesson Plans, segment 6 (Box 2)
    - Goals and Lesson Plans: Theory, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Handbook for Tutors of Reading, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Introduction, segment A, 1979; draft copy (Box 2)
    - Language Experience, segment B, 1979; draft (Box 2)
    - Learn to Read / Root, Jane H., 1973
      - Books 1-4, units 1-20, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Books 6-7, units 26-35, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Phonics, segment D, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Segment K-3 of Basic Reading Tutor Training Workshop on Additional Teaching Techniques for Special Reading Problems, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Tutor Training Workshop
      - [General], 2 folders (Box 3)
      - [Miscellaneous], Feb 1977 (Box 3)
      - [Miscellaneous], 1981; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Lesson Plans and Goals, 1981; 2nd draft (Box 3)
      - Props (Box 3)
      - Segments F(b), G (Box 3)
      - Slide/Tape Script (Box 3)
      - Sight Words, Segment C, 1981; draft (Box 3)
      - Small Group Tutoring Manual (Box 3)
      - Task Force (Box 4)
      - Trainee Kit (Box 4)
      - Video, 1985; 4 folders (Box 4)
      - Video, correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - Word List, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Word Patterns, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Workshop, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Workshop Leaders Handbook (Box 5)
  - "Be Informed on Banking." Gibbs, Elsie, Laubach Literacy International, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Bibliography, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Board of Directors, 1976-1978; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Brochures (Box 5)
  - California, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Case Conference Report (Box 5)
  - Coalition for Literacy, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Colvin, Ruth J., See Colvin, Ruth J. sections following the General Files.
  - Community Education, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Comprehension and Study Skills (Box 5)
  - Comprehension and Study Skills Handbook / Root, Jane
    - [General], 3 folders (Box 5)
    - [General], 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Comments, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Notes (Box 6)
    - Notes and Activities, 1978 (Box 6)
    - Review Task Force, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Conferences
    - Adult Basic Education [ABE], "Renewing Our Resources.", Apr. 2-6, 1984 (Box 6)
    - Adult Education. "The Maine Opportunity", Sep. 15-17, 1983 (Box 6)
    - ALA
      - ALA Midwinter (Denver), Jan. 23-28, 1982 (Box 7)
      - [Unidentified], June 1984 (Box 7)
    - Annual
      - [General], 1975; 1977; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - "Literacy Empowers.", Oct. 2-4, 1985 (Box 7)
      - "Turning the Tide Toward Literacy, Nov. 2-4, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Migrants, Feb. 28, 1984 (Box 7)
    - "Right to Read." IRA, May 12-13, 1976 (Box 7)
    - Teaching English to Speakers of Other Languages [TESOL], May 1982 (Box 7)
    - Conferences. Virginia, May 1983 (Box 7)
  - Consultants (Box 7)
  - Constitution (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    - [General], 1978-1986 (Box 7)
    - Commendations, 1965-1975 (Box 7)
    - CORE Library, 1984-1985 (Box 7)
    - Genegraphics, 1983-1984 (Box 7)
    - Monti, David A., 1980 (Box 7)
    - "Read All About It", 1985 (Box 7)
    - Root, Jane, 1974 (Box 7)
    - Special Reading Problems Modules, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Sadkin, Loretto, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Video, New Jersey, 1981-1985 (Box 8)
  - Directory, 1987-1988 (Box 8)
  - "Do You Understand? Communicating With the Non-English Speaking Patient." Trainers Guide / Carlin, Chip, ed. (comments) (Box 8)
  - English as a Second Language (ESL]
    - [General], 1971-1980; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Bibliography of Basic Materials, 1980 (Box 8)
    - Copyright, 1972-1978 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 8)
    - "I Speak English", 1976; 1985-1986; notes; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Intercultural Understanding (Box 9)
    - New York State Workshop, Aug. 17, 1978 (Box 9)
    - Oral Assessment, 1978 (Box 9)
    - Overview script, 1976 (Box 9)
    - Props, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Scripts, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Trainers Guide, Intercultural Communication, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Tutor Training Workshops, slide/tape scripts; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Financial statements, July 1973-June 1975; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Flash cards (Box 10)
  - Fliers (masters) (Box 10)
  - Flip chart, 1979 (Box 10)
  - Florida, Orange County, funding (Box 10)
  - Gannett brochures, 1980-1985 (Box 10)
  - Gannett Foundation, 1985-1990 (Box 10)
  - Gannett, Newspaper Exhibit, 1983-1984 (Box 10)
  - Glenn, John, 1985 (Box 10)
  - Guidelines, 1971-1973 (Box 11)
  - "Guidelines To Teaching Remedial Reading To the Disadvantaged" / Pope, Lillie, 1967 (Box 11)
  - Hawaii (Box 11)
  - HEW (U. S. Department of Health Education and Welfare)
    - General, 1972-1973 (Box 11)
    - Program Reports, 1973 (Box 11)
    - Proposal, 1973 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1971-1974; 2 foldres (Box 11)
  - Laubach Literacy International, 1973-1977 (Box 11)
  - Laubach Literacy International, 1978-1979 (Box 12)
  - Law Enforcement Assistance Administration (LEAA) (Box 12)
  - "Learning Disabilities Training Module For Teaching Persons With Special Reading Problems", 1975; training module (Box 12)
  - Legislative Committee (Box 12)
  - Legislative Information, 1981-1982; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Library Task Force, 1976-1977 (Box 12)
  - Literacy and Libraries, Wisconsin (Box 12)
  - Literacy Organization Structure (Box 12)
  - LVA (Literacy Volunteers of America), history of (Box 12)
  - Livingston County Awareness Program, 1984 (Box 12)
  - Logo line (Box 12)
  - Management Handbook, distribution, 1983-1984 (Box 12)
  - Mental Retardation Task Force, 1979 (Box 12)
  - Migrants, 1974 (Box 12)
  - Migrants Task Force, 1978-1979 (Box 12)
  - Migrants, tutoring, 1980 (Box 13)
  - "Migrants, Tutoring: An Overview", 1980 (Box 13)
  - Minutes, 1973-1976 (Box 13)
  - Minutes, reports, etc, May 7, 1980 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1969-1970; 1976; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Modern Maturity article, 1977 (Box 13)
  - Monogram (G.E.) article, 1977 (Box 13)
  - NAPCAE (National Association for Public Continuing and Adult Education), 1976-1979 (Box 13)
  - National Center For Voluntary Action, 1974 (Box 13)
  - NEH (National Endowment for the Humanities) project
    - Authors, 1980-1981 (Box 13)
    - Bibliography distribution, 1979 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, Washington D.C, 1978-1979 (Box 13)
    - Expenses, 1978-1979 (Box 13)
    - Grant, 1980-1981 (Box 14)
    - Grant proposal, 1980-1981 (Box 14)
    - Materials Creation Project, 1981; 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Project proposal, 1978-1979 (Box 14)
    - Publishing, 1980-1981 (Box 15)
    - Quarterly Reports, 1980-1981 (Box 15)
    - Questionnaire, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978; 1980-1981; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - National Institute of Education (Box 15)
  - New York City Training, 1987 (Box 15)
  - New York State Department of Correctional Services (Box 15)
  - Newsletters
    - Action (World Association for Christian Communication, 1977-1981 (Box 15)
    - The Affiliate, 1974-1979 (Box 15)
    - Affiliates, 1974-1981; 1988 (Box 15)
    - Pivot (Free Library of Philadelphia), 1979-1980 (Box 16)
    - [Miscellaneous], 1975-1976 (Box 16)
    - [Miscellaneous], 1980-1981 (Box 16)
  - Newspaper as Instructional Tool
    - Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 16)
    - Proposal, 1984 (Box 16)
    - "Tutor's Booklet: The Newspaper As An Instructional Tool for Adult Learners" / Warren, Lucy S and Margaret M. Williams (Box 16)
    - Use, 1981 (Box 16)
    - Workshop participants (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Notebook, calendar, goals (Box 16)
  - Organizational Management Handbook / Haendle, Connie, 1976 (Box 16)
  - Patient Handbook / Carlin, Chip, 1988; comments (Box 16)
  - "Patience", 1988; slide/tape script (Box 16)
  - PEACE (People's Equal Action and Community Effort)
    - Affidavits, 1972-1973 (Box 16)
    - Financial, 1971 (Box 16)
    - Lease, 1973 (Box 16)
  - Permission slips (signed) (Box 17)
  - Personnel. Editorial Assistant Position, 1986 (Box 17)
  - "Preparing and Selecting Printed Material for the New Adult Reader" / Simpson, Edwin L. and Philip W. Leonard, 1976 (Box 17)
  - Prison programs, Florida (Box 17)
  - Program Management
    - Handbook, 1975 (Box 17)
    - Volunteer Program (Box 17)
  - Proposals, 1971 (Box 17)
  - Proposals, 1973-1974; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Props (Box 18)
  - Publicity, 1972-1974 (Box 18)
  - READ (Reading Evaluation Adult Diagnosis)
    - Administrative Guide / Colvin, Ruth and Jane H. Root, 1972 (Box 18)
    - Test, 1979; 1981 (Box 18)
  - "Read All About It!! Tutor-Adults with Daily Newspaper" / Lawson, V.K. with Barbara J. MacDonald and Margaret Williams, 1984; tutor handbook (Box 18)
  - "Read On!" I
    - Biographical info for Jo Ann Schall (workbook author) (Box 18)
    - Book 3, 1976 (Box 18)
    - Copyrights, 1977-1978 (Box 18)
    - Marketing, 1978 (Box 18)
    - Rally, New Jersey, 1980-1981 (Box 18)
    - Reviewers, 1977 (Box 18)
    - Teacher's guide (2 folders), 1978 (Box 18)
    - Workbook 2, 1976 (Box 18)
    - Workbook 4, 1976 (Box 18)
  - "Read On!" II
    - Annotation (Box 18)
    - Annotation chart layout (Box 18)
    - Book 1 (for comment), 1987 (Box 18)
    - Book 1, Office copy/working copy (Box 19)
    - Book 1, Workbook (for comment), 1987 (Box 19)
    - Book 1, Workbook 1: Graphics for workbook (Box 19)
    - Book 2 (for comment), 1987 (Box 19)
    - Book 2: "Musical Mix-up" (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - Book 2, Workbook (for comment), 1987 (Box 19)
    - Book 3 (for comment), 1987 (Box 19)
    - Book 3, Workbook (for comment), 1987 (Box 19)
    - Book 1-3, comments, 1987 (Box 19)
    - Book 5: "Let me tell you a story" (2 folders), 1988 (Box 20)
    - Book 6 (2 folders), 1988 (Box 20)
    - Book 6, Workbook, 1988 (Box 20)
    - Directions for Instruction, 1988 (Box 20)
    - Draft, 1988 (Box 20)
    - General directions, draft (Box 20)
    - Instructor's Guide (1 folder), 1988 (Box 20)
    - Instructor's Guide (3 folders), 1988 (Box 21)
    - Questionaire, 1985 (Box 21)
    - "Report on Activities", 1987 (Box 21)
    - "Sassy", 1987 (Box 21)
    - "Sassy Likes her Work", 1987 (Box 21)
    - "Sassy", workbook (Box 21)
    - Series overview (Box 21)
    - T.A.I. (Text + Akustik = Information) correspondence, 1984 (Box 21)
    - "Tribute to Red", 1987 (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
  - Reader's Digest article, 1975; responses (Box 21)
  - Reading games (Box 21)
  - Refugees, Indochinese Refugee Education Guides (Box 21)
  - Research and Development Committee
    - Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 21)
    - ESL Task Force, 1973-1977 (Box 21)
    - Task Force - Extension TTW (Tutor Training Workshop), 1974; 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous, 1975-1976 (Box 22)
  - Right to Read (National Right to Read Effort)
    - New York City, 1975 (Box 22)
    - Teacher Training Syllabus Reading Academy Out Development (Box 22)
  - Riposo studies, 1974 (Box 22)
  - Skills Files (Box 22)
  - Small Group Tutoring
    - Basic Reading, 1984 (Box 22)
    - Books, 1984 (Box 22)
    - Skills handbook (Box 22)
    - Tutor Training Workshop - Video, 1983 (Box 22)
    - "Tutoring Small Groups: Basic Reading" / Ottson, Gerald (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
  - Special Reading Problems: Some Helps / Miller, Suzanne
    - Drafts, 1983 (Box 23)
    - Trainers Guide, 1983 (Box 23)
    - Tutor Notes, 1983 (Box 23)
  - Speech material, 1966-1975 (Box 23)
  - Staff development project Region V, X
    - Region II, 1974-1975 (Box 23)
    - Region III, 1974 (Box 23)
    - Region V, 1974 (Box 23)
    - Region X, 1974-1975 (Box 23)
  - State Contracts (Box 23)
  - Student Report Cards (Box 23)
  - Tapes Project (Box 23)
  - Tapes reports, 1971-1974 (Box 24)
  - Taylor, R. Steven / Peace Corps, 1984 (Box 24)
  - Teacher Training Workshop, 1972; script, human interest stories (Box 24)
  - Teacher Guides (Box 24)
  - Testing, Oct 1970 (Box 24)
  - "To Read, To Speak, To Live", 1984; promotional slide script (Box 24)
  - Tutor Directions, 1-8 A/B (Box 24)
  - Tutor Training Workshop
    - Children / Raymond, Dorothy (Box 24)
    - ESL, 1976 (Box 24)
  - Tutoring, notes on in-school tutoring (Box 24)
  - Tutoring Reading in Schools
    - Draft scripts and research, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Production, 1981 (Box 24)
    - Script (Box 24)
  - Tutoring, schools (Box 25)
  - Tutoring Techniques, 1980 (Box 25)
  - Tutoring - Telephone (Connecticut), 1984; includes slides (Box 25)
  - United States Office of Education, 1974-1979 (Box 25)
  - Urban Coalition (Box 25)
  - Video Campaign (PBS), 1984 (Box 25)
  - Video Project Proposal, 1981 (Box 25)
  - Video Workshop Trainer's Guide (Box 25)
  - Volunteerism, 1978-1979 (Box 25)
  - "Way With Words: The Story of Literacy Volunteers of America", 1983 (Box 25)
  - "Way With Words: The Story of Literacy Volunteers of America" distribution, 1984 (Box 25)
  - White, Gene (Box 25)
  - Workshop Suggestions, ESL (Box 25)
- Colvin, Ruth J. (I)
  - Australia
    - "Adult Literacy and the Volunteer Tutor." Kindler, Jan, July 1985 (Box 26)
    - Adult Literacy Information Office, 1983 (Box 26)
    - Newsletters, Adult Literacy Information Office, 1985 (Box 26)
    - Articles, 1967-1978 (Box 26)
    - "As It Was Then" / Bruderer, Marian, 1983 (Box 26)
    - Conferences, 10th National, Sep. 4-7, 1986 (Box 26)
    - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 26)
    - "Crossing the Borders " / Bankstown Technical College, 1984 (Box 26)
    - "Family Birthday Picnic", 1984; lva_395 through lva_404; books 1-10, plus some tapes (Box 40)
    - "Guide to Spelling for Tutors of Students" / Stocker, Margrit, 1981 (Box 26)
    - Khmer and Lao Folk Tales / Bankstown Technical College, 1985 (Box 26)
    - "N.S.W. Rules of the Road" / Barbara Gray, Keith White, Jan. 1985 (Box 26)
    - "Newspapers in Education", 1985 (Box 26)
    - "Readings in Adult Basic Education. Australian Council for Adult Literacy (ACAL), 1985 (Box 26)
    - "Spirit of the Khmer" / Bankstown Technical College, 1983 (Box 26)
    - "Still More Jingles" / Marion Bruderer, 1984 (Box 26)
  - Basic Education and Reading Committee (BEAR), 1977-1980 (Box 27)
  - Basic Reading Tutor Training Workshop, Workshop Leaders, Apr 1977 (Box 27)
  - Conferences
    - Annual, Hartford, June 1980 (Box 27)
    - ESL, New York State, Oct. 18-20, 1974 (Box 27)
    - TESOL
      - TESOL, Puerto Rico, May 8-13, 1973 (Box 27)
      - TESOL, Denver, Mar 1974 (Box 27, Box 9)
      - TESOL, Los Angeles, Mar. 6, 1975 (Box 27)
      - TESOL, New York, Mar. 2-7, 1976 (Box 27)
      - TESOL, Urban Literacy, Jan. 21-23, 1988 (Box 27)
  - Conferences/Training, 1974 (Box 27)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1980; 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1981 (Box 28)
  - Culture
    - Chinese (Box 28)
    - Communication (Box 28)
    - Ghana, 1967 (Box 28)
    - Indian Adult Education and the Volunteer Center, Oct. 18-20, 1972 (Box 28)
    - Italian (Box 28)
    - Japanese (Box 28)
    - Spanish speakers (Box 28)
    - Miscellaneous, 1976-1977 (Box 28)
  - ESL
    - "Adult English as a Second Language." Los Angeles City Schools, 1974 (Box 28)
    - Advanced students (Box 28)
    - Aids, 1970 (Box 28)
    - "Bilingual Dictionary as an Aid to Teaching ESL" / Ossoff, Ellen E (Box 28)
    - Comprehension, 1975 (Box 28)
    - Dialog, Sep 1975 (Box 28)
    - Evaluation (Box 28)
    - "I Speak English", 1975; notes (Box 28)
    - Ideas (Box 28)
    - IDIOM (newsletter of New York State ESOL and Bilingual Educators Association), 1973-1974 (Box 29)
    - Institute, Aug. 22-Sep. 2, 1976 (Box 29)
    - Lesson Plans (Box 29)
    - Listening Skills (Box 29)
    - Notes, 1972-1973 (Box 29)
    - Objectives (Box 29)
    - Picture file as aid (Box 29)
    - Programs and Methods (Box 29)
    - Pronunciation (Box 29)
    - Reading, 1977 (Box 29)
    - Sensitivity (Box 29)
    - Survival Skills (Box 29)
    - Teaching English as a Second Language, Unit 5, 1974 (Box 29)
    - Teaching Ideas (Box 29)
    - Techniques (Box 29)
    - Techniques/Substitution Drill (Box 29)
    - Testing (Box 29)
    - Testing Evaluation (Box 30)
    - Tutor Evaluation (Box 30)
    - Tutor Training Workshop [TTW], script for workshop leaders training, Aug. 17, 1978 (Box 30)
    - Workshop leaders training, 1978 (Box 30)
    - Workshop notes (Box 30)
    - Miscellaneous, 1974 (Box 30)
  - Future Training (Box 30)
  - "Handbook for the Teaching of English as a Second Language", 1971 (Box 30)
  - "Helping Adults to Spell" / Moorhouse, Catherine, 1982 (Box 30)
  - "I No Understand the Teacher" / Susan Jacoby, 1975; article (Box 30)
  - Intermedia, 1975-1979 (Box 30)
  - Jewish Community Center, Detroit, Michigan, 1974 (Box 30)
  - Naturalization (Box 30)
  - New Zealand
    - ARAN (Adult Reading Assistance Newsletter), Spring 1985 (Box 31)
    - Brochures, 1983 (Box 31)
    - "Let's Talk Trade", 1983 (Box 31)
    - "Sometimes Teacher, Sometimes Learner: A Guide For Library Tutor Courses", 1980; lva_405; includes tape (Box 40)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1966-1976 (Box 31)
  - Photographs (Box 31)
  - Research and Development Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 31)
  - Sample journal, 1984 (Box 31)
  - Student stories
    - Correctional facilities, 1977-1978 (Box 31)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969-1978; 3 folders (Box 31)
  - Student/Tutor stories (Box 31)
  - "Teaching Adults to Read" / MacFarlane, Tom, Mar. 1986 (Box 31)
  - Turkish
    - "Course in English for Turkish Students" / Nebi, Hope Bersie, 1967 (Box 32)
    - "Pattern Practice Picture Charts" / Nebi, Hope Bersie, mimeographed copy (Box 32)
  - "Tutor. Techniques Used in the Teaching of Reading, Revised Edition" / Colvin, Ruth J. and Root, Jane H., 1976; published edition (Box 32)
  - "Tutor. Techniques Used in the Teaching of Reading, Revised Edition" / Colvin, Ruth J. and Root, Jane H., 1984; published edition (Box 32)
  - "Tutor. Techniques Used in the Teaching of Reading, 6th edition" / Colvin, Ruth J. and Root, Jane H., 1987
    - First draft, copy, 6/10/1987 (Box 32)
    - Second draft, copy, 7/18/1987 (Box 32)
    - First draft, copy, 8/17/1987 (Box 32)
  - Tutor Training